Swastik Biswas

Email: swastikbiswas2016@gmail.com

Self-motivated and a results-oriented Data/ML engineer with 2+ years of professional experience. My interest lies in learning how we use computer vision and image processing to impact people's lives. Real-world scene understanding, activity recognition, anomaly event detection, extreme event forecasting in a computer vision setting are some of the things that are always exciting to me. I am equally enthusiastic about discovering how we can combine computer vision with natural language processing for innovating approaches in which we can extend human interaction with computers.

EDUCATION

Jadavpur University

Kolkata, India

Master of Engineering - Computer Science and Engineering; CGPA: 8.11

August 2017 - June 2019

Mobile: +91-905-1652-880

Thesis: "Volumetric Brain MRI Segmentation using Entropy based Fuzzy clustering algorithm"

Advisor: Prof. Dr. Jamuna Kanta Sing

Visvesvaraya Technological University (VTU)

 $\begin{array}{c} {\rm Bangalore,\ India} \\ {\it August\ 2012\ -\ June\ 2016} \end{array}$

Bachelor of Engineering - Computer Science and Engineering; CGPA: 7.31

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Academic projects

Entropy based Fuzzy clustering algorithm for MR image segmentation Master's Dissertation

Jadavpur University Sep. 2018 - Mar. 2019

Used Shannon entropy to modify the Fuzzy C-Means algorithm for segmenting volumetric brain MR images, model was evaluated on the Brainweb dataset and IBSR dataset before utilizing for the real-patient image volumes.

Gaussian Energy-based function for detection of moving objects in videos

Jadavpur University Feb - May. 2019

Utilized Gaussian distribution to modify energy-based functions in images for motion detection of objects to identify accidents in a real-time video. A dataset consisting of 3320 contain crash frames and 6180 normal frames, ranging from a duration of 3-5min were curated from online sources since there was no public database for vehicle accidents or crash detection. Accuracy achieved during training phase was around 84%.

Deep Learning through Image Analysis of real-time videos

VTU

BE project

Feb. - May.- 2016

Classified entities from real-time videos and presented a comparative study on various models. Image classification was compared on deep belief networks, deep feedforward neural networks, and convolutional neural networks.

Industrial projects

Fuzzy graph networks for building contextualized knowledge graphs **Research project**

BRIDGEi2i Analytics Solutions $May\ 2021$ - Present

Built a labeled property graph that can be used for representing contextual information across various documents. Fuzzy searching algorithms are used along with graph neural networks for achieving better properties on node values. The model is currently used for verification across different data and in different proof-of-concept(POCs).

Automated Driver Assistance Systems

ITC Infotech

Internship

Jul. - Aug. 2015

Developed a real-time video synthesis application on the concept of Automated Driver Assistance Systems for extracting textual information from real-time videos. A CNN model was trained over a custom dataset after evaluating CIFAR-10 and CIFAR-100, for classifying objects of interest. Tesseract OCR was used for extracting any text present in the videos. Accuracy achieved during training and validation phase was around 94% and 89% respectively.

Publications & Presentations

IEEE Conference Papers (Peer-Reviewed)

• S. Biswas, N. Mahata and J. K. Sing, "A New Entropy Based Fuzzy Clustering Algorithm for Volumetric Noisy Brain MR Image Segmentation," 2019 Fifteenth International Conference on Information Processing (ICINPRO), 2019, pp. 1-4.

Professional Experience

Lead Data/ML Engineer - BRIDGEi2i Analytics Solutions

Jul. 2019 - Present

• Data Federated Services Platform

Dec. 2020 - Present

Building data federated platform for one of the largest American multinational Platform-as-a-Service companies with the scope of providing an integrated customer recommendation experience. Along with GloVe vectors for similarity, BERT fine-tuned on a custom dataset is used as a recommendation model with a validation accuracy of approximately 91%. Currently, the production platform handles data at a scale of over 10TB daily with the scope of increase in the future.

• Market share prediction (POC)

Oct. - Dec. 2019

Stochastic differential equation with Gaussian approximation was used for POC focused on understanding the market trend using the sales information for one of the largest British multinational beverage alcohol companies. By performing the simulations for each subsequent point and with a given threshold value, the range of the next value was found. The process is used for identifying anomalous data points within a given window frame. The use case originally had 34 key performance indicators(KPIs) before trimming to 28 KPIs and involved a monthly data refresh of approximately 3GB.

• Data modelling and analysis

Aug. - Dec. 2019

Built ingestion pipelines, prepared denormalized data, and utilized residual sum of squares to detect change points for identifying a level shift in the time series data (in the HR domain) for one world's leading professional services firms. Also, KNN causal estimation was used for determining the causal strength of KPIs after using partial correlation to define independence between the variables. The use case involved had 22 KPIs along with a monthly data refresh of roughly 25GB.

• Logistics Demand analysis

Jan. - Jul. 2020

Used the exponential moving average for detecting anomalies in the historical logistics data for a leading Indian consumer goods company. Furthermore, relationships across various KPIs were determined using mutual information and the chi-square test across the variables. Originally the project started with 7 KPIs and was later increased to 15 KPIs with a bi-weekly data refresh of around 2GB.

• Data Ingestion and Topic modelling

Iul - Dec 2019

Along with building pipelines for data ingestion in Talend and preparing the data model, I was involved in performing topic modeling and sentiment analysis on text data of call transcripts for one of the largest American telecommunications organizations. The pipelines involved real-time model scoring with a daily data refresh of about 3-5TB.

Professional Certifications AND Achievements

Natural Language Processing Specialization by DeepLearning.AI Coursera Deep Learning Specialization by DeepLearning.AI 02 Aug, 2021

Coursera

Preparing for Google Cloud Certification: Cloud Data Engineer Coursera

29 Apr, 2021

Awards from Technology Labs

BRIDGEi2i Analytics Solutions

Individual award for Above and Beyond performance in 4th Quarter of financial year 2020: 23 Feb, 2021
 Team Award for outstanding performance in 2nd Quarter of financial year 2020: 13 Aug, 2020

• Team Award for outstanding performance in 2nd Quarter of financial year 2019:

10 Sep, 2019

SCHOLARSHIPS & GRANTS

• AICTE PG Scholarship

2017 - 19

Post-Graduation scholarship provided by AICTE

SERB, DST. Govt. of India

2018 - 19

Research grant by Dept. of Science & Technology

TECHNICAL SKILLS

• Languages: Python, Java, C, C++, Go, JavaScript, HTML, CSS

• Frameworks: Flask, FastAPI, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Apache Solr, Elasticsearch, Spring, Express JS, Bootstrap

• Tools: Git, Docker, Kubernetes, Talend, Jenkins, Jira

ACTIVITIES & INTEREST

Literature, Art, Coding, Cycling, Travelling